Frances Fox Piven Papers, 1957-2011
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
- SERIES IV. COMMUNITY SERVICE (circa 1964- )
  - Policy Alternatives for the Caribbean and Central America (PACCA)
    - Clippings and articles, circa 1986-87 (Box 62, Folder 3)
    - Domestic Roots of American Foreign Policy pamphlet series
      - Civil Liberties (Box 62, Folder 4)
      - The Constitution (Box 62, Folder 5)
      - Immigration (Box 62, Folder 6)
      - Labor (Box 62, Folder 7)
    - Drafts of pamphlet materials
      - Norma Chinchilla, "Central American Migration in the United States," 1986 (Box 62, Folder 8)
      - [Van Gosse], "The North American Front of the Central American Struggle," 1987 (Box 62, Folder 9)
      - "1985 Perspectives for Work Concerning Nicaragua," 1985 (Box 62, Folder 10)
      - "An Alternative Future for Central America," n.d. (Box 62, Folder 11)
      - "Five Nations/Five Realities," n.d. (Box 62, Folder 12)
      - Unidentified manuscript on labor unions, the international economy, and pro-worker foreign policy (Box 62, Folder 13)
  - "Popular Power in Post-Industrial Society," CUNY Conference, Feb 1989
    - Conference planning correspondence, 1987-89 (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - Budget materials (Box 63, Folder 2)
    - Piven's notes on conference papers (Box 63, Folder 3)
    - Post-conference correspondence with participants, 1989 (Box 63, Folder 4)
    - Post-conference correspondence with Wagner Institute, 1989-90 (Box 63, Folder 5)
    - Conference papers: Drafts and editorial comments, authors A-Z (Box 63, Folder 63a-63b)
      [see also SERIES VIII, AUDIOVISUAL--audiotapes, and SERIES V. WRITINGS, for manuscripts eventually published as Labor Parties in Post-Industrial Society]
  - Socialist Scholars Conference: program, 1991 (Box 64, Folder 1)
  - Social Science Research Council: correspondence, memoranda, and prospectus, "Power, Culture and Place: Essays on New York City," circa 1982 (Box 64, Folder 2)
  - Society for the Study of Social Problems, 1976-82 (Box 64, Folder 3-6)
  - United Nations Expert Study Group: memorandum, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 7)
  - Urban Social Services Research Group (Bellagio Group): correspondence, 1974-75 (Box 64, Folder 8)
  - Workers' Association for Guaranteed Employment (WAGE): correspondence, funding proposal, and clippings, 1982 [Includes "A Short History of WAGE Victories"] (Box 64, Folder 9)
  - Wagner Institute
    - Memoranda and proposals, 1987-88 (Box 64, Folder 10)
    - New York City electoral study: correspondence, notes, reports, and clippings, 1988-89 (Box 64, Folder 11)
    - Publications, 1989-90 (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - Welfare reform/lobbying activity
    - Testimony, Council of the City of New York Sub-Committee on Welfare Hearings, 1967 (Box 65, Folder 2)
    - Fordham University Peer Exchange Program, 1994 (Box 65, Folder 3)
    - Personal Responsibility Act: organizational responses (Box 65, Folder 4)
    - General correspondence, 1994-95 (Box 65, Folder 5)
  - Welfare Warriors, VisionQuest Film and Video Production: correspondence and printed material, 1997 (Box 65, Folder 6)
    [See SERIES VIII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS for video cassette]
  - "Women and the Transformation of the Welfare State" research group: correspondence, papers, and funding proposals, 1983-89 (Box 65, Folder 7)
  - Women to Women on Welfare Reform (CUNY TV Forum, 1994): correspondence, memoranda, and research materials (Box 65, Folder 8)
    [see SERIES VIII, AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS, for video cassette]
  - Working Papers: correspondence, 1978 (Box 65, Folder 9)
  - World Research, Inc.: "The Poverty Trap,": script and related correspondence, circa 1982 (Box 65, Folder 10)
  - Yale Law and Policy Review: editorial board correspondence, 1984 (Box 65, Folder 11)
- SERIES V. WRITINGS (circa 1962- )
  - "The Function of Research in the Formation of City Planning Policy: A Case Study" (Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Chicago, 1962) (Box 66, Folder 1-2)
  - Books
    - Unpublished
      - "Urban Fiscal Crisis"
        - Correspondence, notes, and drafts, 1971-80 (Box 66, Folder 3-5)
        - Contract with Sage Publishing, 1977 (Box 66, Folder 6)
        - Proposals
          - "The Political Management of Urban Fiscal Crisis": notes, outlines, and correspondence, circa 1976 (Box 66, Folder 7)
          - Robert A. Alford, Roger Friedland and Piven, "The Political Management of Urban Crisis," circa 1976 (Box 66, Folder 8)
          - National Science Foundation: drafts, notes, and correspondence, 1978 (Box 67, Folder 1)
          - "Research Pre-Proposal to Study Theories of Social Change.. .": drafts, notes and correspondence, 1979 (Box 67, Folder 2)
        - Notes, research, and draft material
          - Draft material, circa 1977 (Box 67, Folder 3)
          - "Hypotheses": correspondence, notes, and draft material, circa 1977 (Box 67, Folder 4)
          - "Political Conflict, Urban Structure and the Fiscal Crisis," Roger Friedland, Robert Alford, and Piven, circa 1979 (Box 67, Folder 5)
          - Notes, 1979, n.d. (Box 67, Folder 6)
          - "Urban Fiscal Crisis," paper presented to "The Future of Older Metropolitan Areas," Buffalo, NY, n.d. (Box 67, Folder 7)
          - Conference paper, "The Future of Older Metropolitan Areas," Buffalo, NY, n.d. (Box 67, Folder 8)
        - Articles on fiscal crisis
          - Troy C. Armstrong, "Bureaucracy and Politics in Chicago," 1974 (Box 67, Folder 9)
          - David [Gordon?], draft material, circa 1976 (Box 67, Folder 10)
          - John Lojkne, "The Crisis of Local Hegemony," 1980 (Box 67, Folder 11)
          - Guido Martinotti, "Local Financial Problems in Italy," 1978 (Box 67, Folder 12)
          - Mattera and Demac, "Developing and Underdeveloping in New York," 1977 (Box 67, Folder 13)
          - John B. McKinlay, "The Confinement of Non-Options" (Box 68, Folder 1)
          - Peter Messeri, "The Urban Fiscal Crisis and the Fortunes of the Police During the 1960s," 1975 (Box 68, Folder 2)
          - John Mollenkopf, "The Post-Industrialization of U.S. Cities," chapter draft, n.d. (Box 68, Folder 3)
          - K. Newton, "The Local Resource Squeeze" (Box 68, Folder 4)
          - Terry Nichols, "Urban Fiscal Strain," 1978 (Box 68, Folder 5)
          - Guenther Schaefer, "Trends in Local Government and Finance in Germany Since 1950," 1978 (Box 68, Folder 6)
    - Published
      - Regulating the Poor (New York: Vintage), 1971
        - Revision materials (Box 68, Folder 7)
        - Reviews (Box 68, Folder 8-9)
      - The New Class War: Reagan's Attack on the Welfare State and its Consequences (New York: Pantheon Books), 1982
        - Comments and notes (Box 69, Folder 1)
        - Reviews (Box 69, Folder 2)
      - The Mean Season: The Attack on the Welfare State (New York: Pantheon), 1987 [with Cloward, Barbara Ehrenreich, and Fred Block]: drafts and notes (Box 69, Folder 3-4)
      - Why Americans Don't Vote (New York: Pantheon Books,) 1988
        - Research and materials (Box 69, Folder 5)
        - "Democracy Thwarted: Why So Many Americans Don't Vote": draft (Box 69, Folder 6-8)
      - Labor Parties in Post-Industrial Society (Cambridge, UK: Polity Press), 1991
        - Correspondence, 1989-92 (Box 70, Folder 1-2)
        - Draft materials (Box 70, Folder 3-5)
        - Drafts of essays (Box 70, Folder 6-8)
        - Proofs and editorial correspondence (Box 70, Folder 9)
        - Reviews from publisher (Box 70, Folder 10)
      - The Breaking of the American Social Compact (1997)
        - Correspondence, notes, clippings, and research materials (Box 71, Folder 1)
        - Outlines, introduction, and epilogue drafts (Box 71, Folder 2)
  - Articles, [see APPENDIX for list of articles by subject]
    - "The Public Interest in Urban Renewal": proposal drafts and budget proposals, 1962 (Box 72, Folder 1)
    - "Institutional Analyses: Divergent Conceptions of Welfare," Jun 1962 (Box 72, Folder 2)
    - "Low-Income People and Political Process," with Richard A. Cloward (hereafter RAC), Apr 1964 (Box 72, Folder 3)
    - "Conceptual Themes in the Formation of Mobilization for Youth": drafts and correspondence, 1965 (Box 72, Folder 4)
    - "Politics, Professionalism and Poverty," with RAC: drafts, 1965 (Box 72, Folder 5)
    - "Resident Participation in Community Action Programs: An Overview," 1965 (Box 72, Folder 6)
    - "The Professional Bureaucracies Benefit Systems as Influence Systems," with RAC, 1965 (Box 72, Folder 7)
    - "Breaking up the Ghetto: Desegregation or Redistribution," circa 1966 (Box 72, Folder 8)
    - "The Worsening of Ghetto Housing," circa 1966 (Box 72, Folder 9)
    - Untitled manuscript on ghetto housing, circa 1966 (Box 72, Folder 10)
    - "The Case Against Urban Desegregation," circa 1966 (Box 72, Folder 11)
    - "Desegregation: How the Ghetto Pays for the Reformers' Ideal," with RAC: drafts, research materials, correspondence, and memo response from George Wiley, 1966-67 (Box 72, Folder 12)
    - "Organizing the Poor: How it Can be Done," with RAC: Feb 1966 (Box 72, Folder 13)
    - "Echoes from the 'Old Left:' A Comment of the Mobilization for Youth Fiasco," with RAC: drafts, notes, and research materials, 1965 (Box 72, Folder 14)
    - "The Weight of the Poor: A Strategy to End Poverty," with RAC, 1966 (Box 73, Folder 1)
    - "A Strategy to End Poverty," with RAC, 1966 (Box 73, Folder 2)
    - "Poverty, Injustice, and the Welfare State," with RAC, 1966 (Box 73, Folder 3)
    - "Participation of Residents in Neighborhood Community Action Programs," 1966 (Box 73, Folder 4)
    - "Desegregated Housing: Who Pays for the Reformers' Ideal?" with RAC, 1966 (Box 73, Folder 5)
    - Review, Cities: A Scientific American Book, 1966 (Box 73, Folder 6)
    - "Private Benevolence and the Welfare State; The Founts of Social Welfare," 1966 (Box 73, Folder 7)
    - "Professionalism as a Political Skill: The Case of a Poverty Program," 1966 (Box 73, Folder 8)
    - Reply, RAC and Piven, to Reissman, re: "The Guaranteed Income," 1966 (Box 73, Folder 9)
    - "The Demonstration Project: A Federal Strategy for Local Change," in Broyer and Purcell, eds., Community Action Against Poverty. circa. 1967 (Box 73, Folder 10)
    - "The House Deals with the Poor": clippings, correspondence and text, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 11)
    - "The New Metropolitan Politics: How the Negro Will Lose," with RAC: drafts and correspondence, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 12)
    - "Political-Science Content and the Social Work Curriculum: Some Further Comments," correspondence, drafts, and conference program, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 13)
    - "The Case Against Urban Desegregation," with RAC, 1967. (Box 73, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous writings on the origins of the welfare rights movement, circa. 1967 (Box 73, Folder 15)
    - "Comments on [Victor Palmieri's essay] 'Hard Facts About the Future of Our Cities'," 1967 (Box 73, Folder 16)
    - "The Weapon of Poverty: Birth of a Movement," with RAC, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 17)
    - "Separatism Versus Integration; A Rejoinder," with RAC, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 18)
    - "We've Got Rights! The No-Longer Silent Welfare Poor," with RAC, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 19)
    - "Women and Children Last," with RAC, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 20)
    - "Black Control of Cities: Heading It Off by Metropolitan Government," with RAC, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 21)
    - "Ghetto Redevelopment: Corporate Imperialism for the Poor," with RAC, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 22)
    - "Improving Social Welfare: Using Available Resources," with RAC, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 23)
    - "Rent Strike: Disrupting the Slum System," with RAC, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 24)
    - "Starving in Mississippi," with RAC, The Nation, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 25)
    - "Le Burocrazie professionali: il sistema assistenziale come sistema di influenza," with RAC, 1967 (Box 74, Folder 1)
    - "Professionalism as a Political Skill: The Case of a Poverty Program," 1967 (Box 74, Folder 2)
    - "A Visit to Cuba": correspondence, memoranda, and draft, 1968 (Box 74, Folder 3)
      [see also SERIES VII. SUBJECTS)
    - "Uncivil Servants," with RAC, 1968 (Box 74, Folder 4)
    - "What Change for Black Power," with RAC, 1968 (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - "Dilemmas in Social Planning: A Case Inquiry," 1968 (Box 74, Folder 6)
    - "Disrupting City Services to Change National Priorities," with RAC, 1968 (Box 74, Folder 7)
    - "La participacion de los Vecinos en Programas Urbanos de Comunidad," 1968 (Box 74, Folder 8)
    - "Finessing the Poor," with RAC, 1968 (Box 74, Folder 9)
    - "Community Control: Beyond the Rhetoric," 1968 (Box 74, Folder 10)
    - "The Poor Against Themselves," with RAC, 1968 (Box 74, Folder 11)
    - "Migration, Politics and Welfare," with RAC, 1968 (Box 74, Folder 12)
    - "Federal Intervention in The Cities: The New Urban Programs as a Political Strategy," in Handbook for the Study of Social Problems, 1968 (Box 74, Folder 13)
    - "Public Employees and the Ghetto," with RAC: draft, clippings, and correspondence, 1968 (Box 74, Folder 14)
    - "Social Planning or Politics": draft and correspondence, 1968 (Box 74, Folder 15)
    - "Militant Civil Servants in New York City," 1969 (Box 74, Folder 16)
    - "Advocacy as a Strategy of Political Management," 1969 (Box 74, Folder 17)
    - "Whose 'Maximum Feasible Misunderstanding'?," reply to Moynihan, 1969 (Box 74, Folder 18)
    - New York Free Press articles: four-part series on how to organize a Rent Strike, with RAC, 7 Nov 1968; 15 Nov 1968; 29 Dec 1968-9 Jan 1969, and 16 Jan 1969; also, "The Arden House Affair," Westside News, 9 Nov 1967; Westside News 22 Jun 1967. (Box 74, Folder 19)
    - "Whom does the Advocate Planner Serve?": correspondence, drafts, responses, and rejoinder, 1969-70 (Box 74, Folder 20)
    - "Comprehensive Social Planning: Curriculum Reform or Professional Imperialism," 1970 (Box 74, Folder 21)
    - "The Great Society as Political Strategy," 1970 (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - "New Directions for Established Institutions," published panel with Peter Weiss, Rev. Howard R. Moody, and Leonard Buder, Piven moderator, 1970 (Box 75, Folder 2)
    - "Welfare I: A Political Response," Op-Ed with RAC, 1971 (Box 75, Folder 3)
    - "The Perils of Relief Reform for the Poor," Op-Ed with RAC, 1971 (Box 75, Folder 4)
    - "The Relief of Welfare," with RAC, 1971 (Box 75, Folder 5)
    - "How the Federal Goverment Caused the Welfare Crisis," with RAC, 1971 (Box 75, Folder 6)
    - "The Urban Crisis: Who Got What, and Why," 1971 (Box 75, Folder 7)
    - "Short Versions, Urban Crisis": drafts entitled "Why are Cities Going Broke," "The Urban Fiscal Crisis, or, Who Got What and Why," "The Urban Crisis: I., A Matter of Services or Politics?," 1972 (Box 75, Folder 8)
    - Comment, New York University Public Service Employment Conference session on "Dangers, Issues and Directions," 1972 (Box 75, Folder 9)
    - "Social Work Individualizers on the Highways and Byways and at the Crossroads of the Urban Crisis," review of Meyer, Social Work Practice, 1972 (Box 75, Folder 10)
    - "The (Retroactively) Disasterous Consequences of the Welfare Explosion," with RAC: correspondence and draft, 1972 (Box 75, Folder 11)
    - "Who Gets What: Cutting Up the City Pie," 1972 (Box 75, Folder 12)
    - "Nathan Glazer's Retroactive Wisdom on Welfare," with RAC, 1972 (Box 75, Folder 13)
    - Forward, Larry Bailis' Bread or justice: grassroots organizing in the welfare rights movement, 1973 (Box 75, Folder 14)
    - Review of George, Social Security and Society, 1973 (Box 75, Folder 15)
    - Review of Howell, Hard Living on Clay Street: Portraits of Blue Collar Families, 1973 (Box 75, Folder 16)
    - Review of Fellman and Brandt, The Deceived Majority, 1973 (Box 75, Folder 17)
    - "Good Old Golden Rule Days," review of Greer, The Great School Legend, 1973 (Box 75, Folder 18)
    - "Social Science and Social Policy," 1974 (Box 75, Folder 19)
    - "The Political Uses of "Planning" and "Decentralization" in the United States": correspondence and drafts, 1974 (Box 75, Folder 20)
    - "Planning for Women in the Central City," drafts, American Society of Planning Officials correspondence and workshop materials, "Planning for Women," 1973-74 (includes response to paper by June Jordan) (Box 75, Folder 21)
    - "Planning and Class Interests," 1975 (Box 75, Folder 22)
    - Review, Harrington's The Other America: draft and correspondence, 1975 (Box 75, Folder 23)
    - Review, Ginzberg and Solow's The Great Society, 1975 (Box 75, Folder 24)
    - "Regulating the Poor in the 1970s": correspondence and transcription of seminar, 1975 (Box 75, Folder 25)
    - "The Social Worker as Advocate": correspondence and drafts, 1975 (Box 76, Folder 1)
    - "Boston University News Articles": correspondence and drafts, possibly by Howard Zinn; also, "The Ambiguity of Excellence," by Piven, Howard Zinn, and Murray Levin (Box 76, Folder 2)
    - "Commentary on the Cleveland Policy Planning Report": correspondence, drafts, and research materials, 1975 (Box 76, Folder 3)
    - Untitled manuscript of paper presented at "Beyond Civil Rights: The Right to Economic Security," Notre Dame, 1975; also, correspondence, transcript of panel on "Welfare Reform and the Redistribution of Wealth: The Right to an Adequate Income," and paper by Piven, "Welfare Reform and the Redistribution of Income." (Box 76, Folder 4)
    - "The Urban Crisis as an Arena for Class Mobilization," with RAC: correspondence and drafts, 1976 (Box 76, Folder 5)
    - Review of Wilensky, The Welfare State and Equality, 1976 (Box 76, Folder 6)
    - Reply to Moynihan, with RAC, 1977 (Box 76, Folder 7)
    - "Welfare Reform Again," Op-ed with RAC, 1977 (Box 76, Folder 8)
    - Reply to Roach and Roach, with RAC, 1978 (Box 76, Folder 9)
    - "The Urban Crisis," 1978 (Box 76, Folder 10)
    - "Social Policy and the Formation of Political Consciousness," with RAC: drafts, commentary, and correspondence, 1978; also translation of manuscript into German (Box 76, Folder 11)
    - "Hidden Protest: The Structuring of Female Deviance," with RAC: draft, printed material, and correspondence, 1978 (Box 76, Folder 12)
    - "Electoral Instability, Civil Disorder, and Relief Rises: A Reply to Albritton," with RAC: correspondence and drafts, 1978 (Box 76, Folder 13)
    - "Why Ordinary People Sometimes Rebel," Op-ed on Boston University and John Silber," 1978 (Box 76, Folder 14)
    - Review, Tabb and Sawers' Marx and the Metropolis, 1979 (Box 76, Folder 15)
    - Untitled essay on the future of public welfare for Public Welfare, 1979 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - Review of Schlozman and Verba, Injury to Insult, 1979 (Box 77, Folder 2)
      (see also paper co-authored with Roger Friedland, Robert Alford, and John Mollenkopf, "Governing Coalition and Precarious Resources: Structural Change and the State," circa 1979, filed under Writings, Urban Fiscal Crisis)
    - Untitled Op-ed, circa 1980 (Box 77, Folder 3)
    - "Capital Against Democracy," 1981 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - "Moral Economy and the Welfare State," with RAC: drafts, 1981 (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - "Public Choice and Private Power: A Theory of Fiscal Crisis," with Roger Friedland: correspondence and drafts, 1981-82 (Box 77, Folder 6)
    - "The American Road to Democratic Socialism," with RAC: correspondence, notes, and drafts, 1982 (Box 77, Folder 7)
    - Untitled manuscript on the meaning of war; also, paper and Op-ed by Seymour Melman on "The Permanent War Economy," 1982 (Box 77, Folder 8)
    - "Social Breakdown and Social Solidary [sic] Theories of Protest Movements," with RAC, 1982 (Box 77, Folder 9)
    - "The Transformation of City Politics," 1982 (Box 77, Folder 10)
    - "The Myth of Academic Freedom": drafts and correspondence, 1982 (Box 77, Folder 11)
    - "The Reagan Attack on the Welfare State" (Box 77, Folder 12)
      (see SERIES IV, COMMUNITY SERVICE-Institute for Policy Studies)
    - "Prospects for a Resurgent Democratic Left: Responses to Walter Dean Burnham," ("The Reagan Revolution and the Eclipse of the Democratic Party"): drafts and correspondence, 1981 (Box 77, Folder 13)
    - "Ideas, Protest and Humanitarianism," 1983 (Box 78, Folder 1)
    - "Toward a Class-Based Realignment of American Politics: A Movement Strategy," with RAC, 1983 (Box 78, Folder 2)
    - Untitled article for Mother Jones' campaign '84 special issue, and special issue proposal, 1984 (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - "Disruption and Organization: A Rejoinder" (to Gamson, "Organizing the Poor"): drafts and correspondence, 1983-84 (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - "Trying to Break down the Barriers," with RAC, 1985 (Box 78, Folder 5)
    - Untitled manuscript on voter registration, with RAC, circa 1985, (possibly for The Nation) (Box 78, Folder 6)
    - "The Executive Action Strategy," with RAC, galley for The Nation, 1985 (includes "Part II," probably of above) (Box 78, Folder 7)
    - "Toward a Just and Adequate Welfare State: Philosophical and Programmatic Perspective," with Barbara Ehrenreich, 1985 (Box 78, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence and outlines for book with Fred Block and Barbara Ehrenreich on the attack on social welfare, 1985-87 (Box 78, Folder 9)
    - "The Trouble with Full Employment," with RAC, Barbara Ehrenreich, and Fred Block, 1988: drafts, correspondence, and research materials (Box 78, Folder 10)
    - "Welfare Reform Impact on Women and Families," 1987 (Box 78, Folder 11)
    - Review, Weir, et al., The Politics of Social Policy in the United States," circa 1988 (Box 78, Folder 12)
    - "Popular Politics and Social Policy in the United States," 1988 (Box 78, Folder 13)
    - "Gender, Power, and Welfare: A Reply to Linda Gordon,"with RAC, 1988 (Box 78, Folder 14)
    - "What Happened to the Promise of Women's Power: The Case of American Social Policy," 1988 (Box 78, Folder 15)
    - Untitled manuscript on voter turnout, circa 1989 (Box 78, Folder 16)
    - "Why Voter Turnout is Low, and Falling," 1989: drafts and comments by Raymond Wolfinger (Box 78, Folder 17)
    - "Ideology and the State: Women, Power and the Welfare State": correspondence and page proofs, 1989 (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - "Planning, Power, Politics and People": correspondence and panel transcript, 1990 (Box 79, Folder 2)
    - "The American Democratic Party," 1990 (Box 79, Folder 3)
    - "Welfare State Policies in the United States": drafts and correspondence, 1990-91, and conference program, "First All-European Dialogue on Social Policies," Helsinki, March 1990 (Box 79, Folder 4)
    - "Why Turnout is Low, and Falling: The Multiple Determinants of NonVoting in the United States,": paper and correspondence, 1991; and "Rules, Parties and Political Attitudes: The Multiple Determinants of NonVoting in the United States," 1991 (Box 79, Folder 5)
    - Essay on patriotism for The Nation, with RAC, 1991 (Box 79, Folder 6)
    - "Race, Liberals, the Democratic Party," circa 1991 (Box 79, Folder 7)
    - "The Mayors and the Federal System," circa 1991 (Box 79, Folder 8)
    - "Reforming the Welfare State": drafts, circa 1992 (Box 79, Folder 9)
    - "Ideology, Disruption and Movement Power: Preliminary Notes;" "Gender and the Future of Welfare State;" "Movements and Dissensus Politics": correspondence (Box 79, Folder 10)
    - Paper for "Conference on Justice and Human Rights Advocacy," drafts, correspondence, and copies of other conference papers, 1993 (Box 79, Folder 11)
    - "Welfare Reform and the New Class War": correspondence and editorial materials for Unmasking Social Inequalities (1995), 1993 (Box 79, Folder 12)
    - "The Public Sector Under Seige": draft proposals and correspondence, 1994 (Box 79, Folder 13)
    - "Was Welfare Reform Worthwhile?": text and response by David Ellwood, 1996 (Box 79, Folder 14)
    - "Women in the Welfare State": draft, galleys and correspondence, 1996 (Box 79, Folder 15)